<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>CSS on Jkzmr</title>
        <link>https://jankazimir.github.io/tags/css/</link>
        <description>Recent content in CSS on Jkzmr</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 15:45:57 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jankazimir.github.io/tags/css/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Choosing Hugo</title>
        <link>https://jankazimir.github.io/post/why-hugo/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 15:45:57 +0200</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://jankazimir.github.io/post/why-hugo/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When it came time to create this website, I did the &lt;em&gt;very 2025&lt;/em&gt; thing and asked gemini how to go about it.  The answer actually made sense and I began, as suggested, by brainstorming some features and drawing up a wireframe.
I knew what I wanted: a landing page with a blog, a projects page, and a contact/about page. Simple, and I knew how to make a static page in VScode and push it to GitHub to deploy it, all from my CodeCademy &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://jankazimir.github.io/pages/about/#&amp;amp;gid=1&amp;amp;pid=2&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;course&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a mock up, complete with weird colours (so I could see my flex boxes), and I was up and running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I was linking the pages together, I began to realise that some of this was going to become a chore. The mockup was done, but far from &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; and it would need a lot of fine tuning to get there. I wasn’t going to make &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; website, what would be the point?  But mostly, aside from a myriad of small flaws, the biggest problem was that my page just wasn’t a blog.
At that point, creating a new post meant creating a new page, editing the html manually, linking from the homepage by editing the html manually, and linking from the blog page, by… You see where this is going.
I could probably use a markdown to html converter, maybe have a template ready for some copy pasting, but it still seemed like a chore. There had to be a better way…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured I had two options : fine tune the design of the mockup, while I learned to implement the features I wanted, or use a template and a static site generator.
[] &amp;gt; Links to static site generator
[] &amp;gt; Link to stack template&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose the latter.&lt;br&gt;
Ultimately I will most likely end up learning both things, but using a template gets me results &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;.
Getting results is nice, getting results &lt;strong&gt;now&lt;/strong&gt; is better.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
